hey everybody, for today's problem we have a
reaction here that I've drawn, this is
this compound reacting with sulfuric
acid to generate this product, and what
we're gonna do is we want to show the
mechanism, that means every single
intermediate and every single electron
pushing arrow, so other than the fact that
we're reacting with with a strong acid i don't
want to give too much away
go ahead and give it a shot
ok so this is a pretty interesting
mechanism let's take a look at what
happens, now we know that this is a
strong acid, it has the capacity to
protonate something. the only thing we're
gonna be able to protonate is this hydroxyl
group so anytime you see an acid-base
reaction, we've got a strong acid, we know
that strong acid is gonna donate a proton so
we want to look at the substrate and say
where's the proton gonna go? well once
again the only thing here that's gonna
work, we have a lone pair on oxygen,
that's the only thing that can
accommodate a proton, so that is gonna
get protonated and now we have basically
a water molecule right here. now whereas
a hydroxyl group is a is a terrible
leaving group, a water molecule is a
great leaving group and we are in acidic
condition so positive charges are ok, so
this water can leave so that if
water leaves, now we're left with a carbocation right here. now this is the
key step, this is a carbocation
rearrangement step. if we remember from
the other lectures we can have a hydride
shift or we can have a methanide
shift where actual alkyl groups are
moving, but the interesting thing here is
that this is gonna be able to rearrange
to turn a secondary carbocation into a
tertiary carbocation and the way
it's going to be able to do it is with
this methanide shift right there. or
it's not really a methyl but an alkyl
shift where this bond is going to
detach from that carbon and reattach
to that carbon so this is what we're
gonna get. this is favorable for two
reasons
number one: we turn a secondary carbocation
into a tertiary carbocation so that's a driving force
but then the other thing we're doing is
turning a five-membered ring into a
six-membered ring, so there's a lot going
on here that makes this a favorable
rearrangement. and so now from the
secondary carbocation we have this
tertiary carbocation, and we are in aqueous acidic
solution so we can always eliminate and
what's going to happen is this can grab
this proton here and form the pi bond
there, and there's our product.
thanks for watching guys, subscribe to my
channel for more tutorials and as always
feel free to email me